Guide to the John McDonald Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Correspondence and Personal Papers, 1926-1999; Series I; 9.42; (10 boxes)
  - General Correspondence
    - Alphabetical
      - Morgenstern, Oskar
        See: Morgenstern, Oskar and Dorothy
      - Neff, Sid, 1984-1996 (Box 2, Folder 67-69)
      - The New York Times, 1975, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      - Osborn, Robert Chesley, 1959-1991 (Box 2, Folder 71)
      - Princeton University, 1960-1979 (Box 2, Folder 72)
      - Rathbone, Belinda A., 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 73)
      - Reuben, William A.
        See: Research files
      - Seligman, Daniel, 1979-1997 (Box 2, Folder 74-75)
      - Sigourney, Andre R., 1989 (Box 3, Folder 76)
      - Slesinger, Tess, 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 77)
        Some correspondence references McDonald's film treatment proposals in Series III
      - Sloan, Alfred P. (Alfred Pritchard)
        See: Series II files for McDonald's books A Ghost's Memoir, and My Life with General Motors.
      - Solow, Herbert, Sylvia Salmi, and Anne, 1942-1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
        For additional material on Herbert Solow, see Series III, American Committee for the Defense of Leon Trotsky (Dewey Commission); see also: Research files
        Includes a photograph of McDonald with Trotsky and Solow in Mexico
      - Stevens, Catharine, 1957-1995 (Box 3, Folder 79-82)
        Additional correspondence from Stevens is filed throughout the Series II files for A Ghost's Memoir and My Years with General Motors.
      - Theodore Gordon Flyfishers, Inc., 1965-1997 (Box 3, Folder 83-84)
      - Trilling, Lionel and Diana, 1947-1968 (Box 3, Folder 85)
      - Trotsky, Leon
        See: Trotsky, Leon
      - Von Neumann, John
        See: Von Neumann, John
      - Wald, Alan
        See also: Solow, Herbert, Sylvia Salmi, and Anne
        - Correspondence, 1974-1989 (Box 3, Folder 86-101)
        - McDonald's notes on Wald, 1974-1989 (Box 3, Folder 102-104)
      - Walker, Adelaide, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 105)
      - Warren, Robert Penn and Eleanor Clark, 1955-1996 (Box 3, Folder 106)
      - Weber, Sara, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 107)
        Includes a typescript draft of an article by Nataliia Ivanovna Trotskaia
      - Wulff, Lee and Joan, 1988-1991 (Box 3, Folder 108)
        See also: Wulff, Lee
      - Yale University Library, 1970-1983 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Chronological
      - Letters of reference, 1936-1937 (Box 4, Folder 110)
        Contains letters from Louis M. Hacker, Peter Monro Jack, Norman Nelson, and Warner G. Rice
      - Rejection letters, 1940, undated (Box 4, Folder 111)
      - Correspondence, 1936-1984 (Box 4, Folder 112-141)
      - Correspondence, 1984 (Box 5, Folder 142-145)
      - Condolence cards and letters (re: Dorothy Eisner), 1984 (Box 5, Folder 146-154)
      - Correspondence, 1985-1987 (Box 5, Folder 155-170)
      - Correspondence, 1988-1991 (Box 6, Folder 171-201)
      - Correspondence, 1991-1994 (Box 7, Folder 202-224)
      - Correspondence, 1994-1998, undated (Box 8, Folder 225-250)
  - Personal Papers
    Arranged alphabetically by file title
    - Calendars (wall), 1973-1998 (Box 9, Folder 251-254)
    - Department store class-action lawsuit documents, 1976 (Box 9, Folder 255)
    - Eisner, Dorothy, 1973-1984 (Box 9, Folder 256-259)
    - Evans, Walker (resume), 1941 (Box 9, Folder 260)
    - Financial papers, 1942-1982 (Box 9, Folder 261-262)
    - Gerald Loeb Award, University of California, Los Angeles, 1976-1978 (Box 9, Folder 263-264)
    - Heart Club of the City of New York, 1951-1957 (Box 9, Folder 265-267)
    - Household bills, 1940-1944 (Box 9, Folder 268)
    - Insurance papers, 1942-1996 (Box 9, Folder 269)
    - Medical papers, 1946-1997 (Box 9, Folder 270-272)
    - Mentions in press, 1984-1997 (Box 9, Folder 273-274)
    - Miscellaneous personal notes and ephemera, 1981-1997, undated (Box 9, Folder 275-280)
      Includes files of papers from envelopes marked "from the mantle", "bulletin board," "addresses and cards from desk," "losing race tickets," reminder notes to self, as well as a series of "reward if found" notes
    - Morrow, Felix, eulogy, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 281)
    - New York Newspaper Guild, 1946-1947 (Box 9, Folder 282)
    - New York (NY), City Planning Commission., 1939 (Box 9, Folder 283)
    - Obituaries and tributes, 1999 (Box 9, Folder 284)
    - Personal chronology, 1920-1937, 1937, undated (Box 9, Folder 285)
    - Personal documents, 1940-1989 (Box 9, Folder 286)
      Contains passports, driver's and fishing licenses, certificate of literacy, World's Fair ticket, and copies of birth certificate
    - Personal letterhead, business cards, undated (Box 9, Folder 287)
    - Photographs
      - Cranberry Island, Maine, undated (Box 9, Folder 288)
      - 80th birthday party, 1986 Dec 29 (Box 9, Folder 289-290)
      - Miscellaneous photographs, circa 1940-1995 (Box 9, Folder 291-292)
        Includes photographs of early fishing trips; party with Charles and Oona Chaplin; McDonald and Solow at racetrack; portraits of McDonald. Childhood photographs (with family members) are filed in Series II, "Detroit" projects
    - Portrait by Enrique Flores-Galbis; oil on linen, 1988 (Box 56)
    - Profile of McDonald by Carl Little, published in Bar Harbor Times, 1996 (Box 10, Folder 293)
    - Profile of McDonald by Dan Seligman, published in Forbes, 1998 Oct 19 (Box 10, Folder 294)
    - Putnam, Anne Eisner, 1967 (Box 10, Folder 295)
    - Real estate papers, 1940-1977 (Box 10, Folder 296)
    - Resumes and autobiographical statements, 1938-1993, undated (Box 10, Folder 297)
    - Social Security papers, 1942-1982, undated (Box 10, Folder 298)
    - Travel files
      - England, 1993 (Box 10, Folder 299-300)
      - Florida, 1979-1982 (Box 10, Folder 301-303)
      - Mexico, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 304)
        Contains postcards sent to Eisner's family and four photographs taken in Mexico
      - Switzerland, 1990 (Box 10, Folder 305)
      - Western United States, 1950 (Box 10, Folder 306)
    - United States, Selective Service Board (New York, NY), 1941-1944 (Box 10, Folder 307)
    - United States, Works Progress Administration, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 308)
    - Will notes, 1976-1978 (Box 10, Folder 309)
- Writings, 1890-1998; Series II; 26; (26 boxes)
  Organized into three subseries: Articles; Books; and Other Writings.
  The series contains correspondence and research files supporting McDonald's writing projects, as well as contracts, drafts, tear sheets, reviews, and fan mail pertaining to his work.
  The Articles subseries holds files covering McDonald's research and writings for the magazines Fortune, The Nation, New York, Rod and Reel, Sports Illustrated, and Town and Country. Material in his books generally had appeared previously in his writings for periodicals, particularly for Fortune, so some of these files have direct intellectual connections to the research and correspondence files in the Books subseries, and vice-versa.
  The subseries primarily contains files from McDonald's twenty-six-year career at Fortune, including correspondence files and internal memoranda related to the magazine's administrative matters. McDonald kept separate correspondence folders for two men, the Princeton economists Oskar Morgenstern and John Von Neumann, perhaps because their relationships spanned so many of his projects. The general correspondence is a chronologically arranged set of single letters on a variety of topics; in many cases carbon copies of McDonald's replies are on file. Also here are the records of the "Fortune Jockey Club," a syndicate of investors (McDonald, fellow Fortune staff members, friends, and family) who purchased a racehorse in 1949. Included are photographs of the filly, Water Kelpie, who ran during the summer of 1950 and was sold by the group that fall.
  Most of the files, however, cover McDonald's writings for the magazine, and include topic-related correspondence, research notes, and drafts, as well as fan mail and newspaper articles that reported on his Fortune articles. Also filed here are several versions of lists recording McDonald's writings and editorial work for Fortune, which have particular value as his contributions did not always appear under a byline. He kept a small selection of tear sheets and loose covers from the magazine, most dating between 1945 and 1955. Notes and lists found with the papers indicate that some of the pages may be part a set of articles pulled together by his Sloan-project associate Catharine Stevens as a 1957 Christmas gift. Full issues of the magazine exist for March 1946, March 1948 (with its original mailing carton), February 1953, August 1957, and September 1963. The latter contains the first installment of the six-part series on Alfred P. Sloan Jr. and General Motors, afterward published as Sloan's My Years with General Motors.
  There are files for four articles that McDonald wrote for Sports Illustrated between 1954 and 1957, including one which appeared in the magazine's August 1954 inaugural issue. McDonald's two 1957 articles on the fifteenth-century fisherwoman Juliana Berners, co-written with Cornell University professor Dwight A. Webster, were later expanded for McDonald's 1964 volume The Origins of Angling. The earliest published work by McDonald in the collection is a short piece on trout fishing that appeared in the May 1939 issue of Town and Country. Additional early writings on fishing, some co-authored with his friend Dan Bailey, can be found in Series III, Other Papers.
  The Books subseries holds documentation on nine books McDonald wrote, co-wrote, or contributed to. The files hold correspondence, contracts, research material, drafts, reviews, royalties statements, and fan mail. As many of his books evolved from his magazine writings, readers should also check the Articles subseries for research materials that might precede those filed in the Books subseries. The largest amount of documentation exists for three projects, The Game of Business, A Ghost's Memoir, and My Years with General Motors, with smaller groups of files for the other six: As It Happened; The Complete Fly Fisherman; Fisherman's Bounty; The Origins of Angling; Quill Gordon; and Strategy in Poker, Business and War.
  A major resource for McDonald's book The Game of Business was a 1968 survey he made of the chief executives of thirty American corporations. The interviews were conducted using a questionnaire on strategic decision-making that he had developed with the assistance of noted academics in the field of game theory at Cornell, New York, Princeton, and Yale universities among others, as well as staff members at the Rand Corporation. The files for those consultations are present in the collection; the notes folders contain McDonald's records of conversations (many of which were afterward typed up) and collected research material. Folders of raw data from McDonald's interviews with the executives follow the academic research files.
  McDonald's files on his writings on General Motors (GM) are divided between his two major works on the topic: the book he wrote with Alfred P. Sloan Jr. ( My Years with General Motors, 1964) and A Ghost's Memoir (published posthumously in 2002), the book about the suppression of the book he wrote with Sloan. In preparing the latter, McDonald pulled many primary documents from his project files for the former, and relied upon them to tell his story of the administrative and legal battles he fought to see the Sloan book published. Readers interested in the preparation of the earlier Sloan work will need to consult the files for both projects. The extensive research files for the 1964 Sloan book include correspondence with (and between) Sloan and GM executives, notes on interviews held and GM records reviewed, copies of GM internal records, and chronologically arranged rounds of manuscript drafts circulated to Sloan, GM executives, and others for comment. Folders holding the drafts retain the titles assigned by McDonald, who had kept many of the texts in hand-labeled spring-clasp binders. Filed at the end is McDonald's annotated copy of the published volume, which he inscribed "Work copy #2."
  When compiling material for his A Ghost's Memoir (begun under the working title "Mr. Sloan"), McDonald organized his notes, correspondence, and documents in a series of chronologically arranged manila envelopes, many of which he annotated with explanatory notes, additional facts, and editorial comments. The envelopes held papers dating from the 1950s and 1960s that he had supplemented with new research and draft texts from the 1970s through the 1990s. McDonald's order has been maintained, with the material filed under the year of the earliest items in the folder; his manila envelopes were retained with their contents when his annotations were more than simply a list of the enclosures. Of particular interest here are McDonald's comprehensive notes of meetings he held with Sloan, as well as those with GM executives and their legal representatives, in the late 1950s and early 1960s. Also here are files holding letters between McDonald and Sloan that span their entire relationship, most of which discusses their contractual agreements regarding McDonald's employment, salary, and royalties from sales of the 1964 book.
  Strategy in Poker, Business and War (1950) had its genesis in two articles he published in Fortune on poker (March 1948) and strategy (June 1949); readers interested in this book should also consult material on the two articles and correspondence with Oskar Morgenstern and John Von Neumann filed in the Series II subseries Articles, Fortune.
  The Other Writings subseries contains material for books and articles that were either works of personal interest or short-term contract jobs; the bulk of the papers document projects that McDonald thought about and never published. The files are arranged under the headings of Fiction and Non-Fiction, and primarily contain research, notes, and correspondence, with only a few drafts of texts. Fiction writings include plans for two unpublished works for children, "Pelican" and "Puffin;" the former was begun in 1941 and revived by McDonald some fifty years later. The majority of the files, however, are for two proposed book-length projects, "Detroit" (non-fiction) and "Hairpin," (fiction) with two smaller groups for novels whose notes McDonald marked, "Story A" and "Epi." McDonald's extensive material for "Hairpin" (sometimes labeled as "Hairpins") consists of loose pages, pads, and notebooks of random notes, thoughts, and quotations, in addition to two actual hairpins; many of the notes appear to relate to his relationship with the artist Rivka Schoenfeld.
  McDonald's literary ruminations on his native city of Detroit spanned five decades. In the late-1930s he had sketched a number of narrative outlines, and had researched and written essay-length drafts of what he termed "a biography of Detroit," into which he intended to weave stories of industrialists, workers, trade union leaders, socialists, and politicians drawn from his experiences in New York. When he took up the project again in the mid-1980s, he focused more on his own childhood memories and ancestors, primarily the McDonald and Perrin families, and the West Village neighborhood in which he grew up; on a "work in progress: 1985-1987" resume, McDonald described the book as "Biography-autobiography: The Twenties and Thirties with extensions back into the 19th Century and forward to the 1980s." The files that he had labeled as "Detroit" contain correspondence with librarians, archivists, church historians, genealogists, and McDonald relatives in the Midwest, Florida, and Canada, as well as maps, photographs, research notes, clippings, photocopies, and a few drafts of text.
  Readers interested in any of McDonald's unpublished works should also consult the chronological run of Logs/Notebooks/Daily Notes held in Series III, many of which may contain further and random notes, sketches, and ideas for these unfinished writing projects.
  - Articles
    Arranged in alphabetical order by periodical title
    - Fortune
      - Agreements, 1970-1975 (Box 11, Folder 310)
      - Anniversary anthology essay, 1979 (Box 11, Folder 311-312)
      - Correspondence
        - Galbraith, John Kenneth, 1967-1971, undated (Box 11, Folder 313)
        - Morgenstern, Oskar and Dorothy, 1947-1978 (Box 11, Folder 314)
        - Von Neumann, John, 1948-1981, undated (Box 11, Folder 315-320)
          Includes notes of their meetings and research on Von Neumann
        - Von Neumann, Klara Dan, 1956-1961 (Box 11, Folder 321)
        - General correspondence, 1946-1974, undated (Box 11, Folder 322-329)
          Correspondence relating to specific articles is filed with their research notes below
      - Essay: "Theory of Editing", 1960, 1983 (Box 11, Folder 330)
      - Internal memoranda, 1948-1958 (Box 11, Folder 331)
      - "Fortune at Work" [staff newsletter], 1946-1953 (Box 11, Folder 332)
      - Fortune Jockey Club, 1948-1952 (Box 11, Folder 333-340)
      - Future stories lists, 1945-1947 (Box 11, Folder 341)
      - "f.y.i." [Time, Inc., staff newsletter], 1947-1951, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 342)
      - Published articles lists, undated (Box 11, Folder 343)
      - Research notes, correspondence, and clippings related to articles
        Arranged in order of publication date
        - "Fly Fishing and Trout Flies," May 1946, 1939-1953 (Box 11, Folder 344-349)
        - "Fly Fishing and Trout Flies," May 1946, 1939-1953 (Box 12, Folder 350-357)
        - "The Yearlings," April 1947 (Box 12, Folder 358)
        - "Poker: An American Game," March 1948 (Box 12, Folder 359)
        - "Atlantic Salmon" and "The Leaper," June 1948, 1947-1952 (Box 12, Folder 360-371)
        - "Champion Paper," January 1949 (Box 12, Folder 372)
        - "Movies: the End of an Era," April 1949, 1948-1949 (Box 12, Folder 373)
        - "A Theory of Strategy," June 1949, 1948-1959 (Box 12, Folder 374-379)
        - Miscellaneous clippings, re: articles, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 380)
        - "The Economists," December 1950, 1950-1951 (Box 12, Folder 381-389)
        - "The War of Wits" [re: the Rand Corporation], March 1951, 1950-1958 (Box 13, Folder 390-393)
        - "French Business Talks Back," April 1952, 1951-1952 (Box 13, Folder 394)
        - "Marcel Boussac: Tycoon," September 1952, 1952-1958 (Box 13, Folder 395-396)
        - "Strategy of the Seller," December 1952 (Box 13, Folder 397)
        - "CBS Steals the Show," July 1953 (Box 13, Folder 398)
        - "Does 'Small Business' Get a Fair Shake?," October 1953 (Box 13, Folder 399)
        - "How to Get a Raise," December 1953 (Box 13, Folder 400)
        - "General LeMay's Management Problem," May 1954 (Box 13, Folder 401)
        - "The Businessman in Government," July 1954 (Box 13, Folder 402)
        - "How Businessmen Make Decisions," August 1955, 1954-1955 (Box 13, Folder 403)
        - "The Business Decision Game," March 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 13, Folder 404-406)
        - "Montgomery Ward: Prosperity is Still Around the Corner," November 1960, 1940-1954 (Box 13, Folder 407-408)
          Files hold only the corporation's annual reports
        - "TWA," May and July 1965, and July 1966, 1965-1966 (Box 13, Folder 409)
        - "Now the Bankers Come to Disney," May 1966 (Box 13, Folder 410-414)
        - "Some Candid Answers from James J. Ling," August and September 1969, 1969-1970 (Box 13, Folder 415-416)
      - Miscellaneous tear sheets, covers, contents pages, notes, 1946-1971, undated
    - The Nation, "Will Hays's New Rival," April 3, 1943 (Box 13, Folder 417)
      File holds just magazine issue
    - New York, "Naked in New York," January 20, 1975, 1974-1990 (Box 13, Folder 418-419)
      Includes Barthian analysis by Adam Vance (McDonald grandson)
    - Rod & Reel, "Dan Bailey: 1904-1982," May/June 1982, 1981-1982 (Box 13, Folder 420-422)
    - Sports Illustrated
      - "The Best Vacation Trout Fishing" [on Montana], August 16, 1954, 1953-1954 (Box 14, Folder 423-424)
      - "A Rare Find: Gordon's Fly Box," October 18, 1954 (Box 14, Folder 425)
      - "The Lady and the Trout," with Dwight A. Webster, May 27 and June 3, 1957
        - Berners' Treatise of Fishing with an Angle ([1515?]), photographs, 1956-1957, undated (Box 14, Folder 426)
        - Correspondence and notes, miscellaneous, 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 427)
        - Duggan, Alfred, 1955-1956 (Box 14, Folder 428)
        - Letters and notes from binder, 1955-1957 (Box 14, Folder 429-432)
        - Issues and tear sheets, 1957 (Box 14, Folder 433)
      - "In Montana: Armstrong's Creek," April 7, 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 14, Folder 434-435)
    - Town and Country, "A Trout Secret," May 1939, 1938-1939 (Box 14, Folder 436)
  - Books
    Arranged in alphabetical order by book title
    - As It Happened: a Memoir, by William S. Paley (1979)
      - Correspondence and notes, 1975-1982 (Box 14, Folder 437-441)
      - Miscellaneous notes, 1975-1980, undated (Box 14, Folder 442-443)
      - Research assistants, 1977-1978 (Box 14, Folder 444)
    - The Complete Fly Fisherman (first edition, 1947)
      - Correspondence
        - Anglers' Club of New York
          See: Von Kienbusch, Carl Otto Kretzschmar
        - Ann Watkins, Inc.
          See: Charles Scribner's Sons
        - Bates, Joseph D., Jr., 1949 (Box 14, Folder 445)
        - Cave, Edward, 1910, 1946-1948 (Box 14, Folder 446)
          Contains one letter from Robert Bright Marston to Cave (1910)
        - Charles Scribner's Sons, 1946-1967 (Box 14, Folder 447-448)
        - Christian, Herman, 1946 (Box 14, Folder 449)
        - Cross, Reuben, 1946-1948 (Box 14, Folder 450)
        - Gordon, Theodora, 1947-1948 (Box 14, Folder 451)
        - Gordon, Theodore
          See: Skues, G. E. M. (George Edward Mackenzie)
        - Hackle, Sparse Grey, 1948-1972, undated (Box 14, Folder 452-454)
        - Marston, R. L., 1946-1948 (Box 14, Folder 455)
        - Marston, Robert Bright
          See: Edward Cave
        - Miller, Alfred W.
          See: Sparse Grey Hackle
        - Skues, G. E. M. (George Edward Mackenzie), 1915, 1946-1948 (Box 14, Folder 456)
          Contains one letter from Theodore Gordon to Skues (1915)
        - Steenrod, Roy, 1915, 1946-1954, undated (Box 14, Folder 457)
          Contains one letter from Theodore Gordon to Steenrod (1915)
        - Von Kienbusch, Carl Otto Kretzschmar, 1945-1963 (Box 14, Folder 458)
        - Wulff, Lee, 1945-1987 (Box 14, Folder 459)
          See also: Wulff, Lee and Joan
        - General correspondence, 1946-1947 (Box 14, Folder 460)
      - Research files
        - Gordon, Theodore
          - Articles and photographs, undated (Box 14, Folder 461)
          - Letters to the Fishing Gazette (1891-1915) and Forest and Stream (1908-1915), photostats, undated (Box 14, Folder 462)
          - Letters to Guy R. Jenkins (1912-1915), transcripts, undated (Box 14, Folder 463)
          - Letters to G. E. M. Skues (1906-1915), transcripts, undated (Box 15, Folder 464-466)
          - Letters to Roy Steenrod (1912-1915), transcripts, undated (Box 15, Folder 467-471)
            See also: Steenrod, Roy
        - Notes, miscellaneous, 1945-1947, undated (Box 15, Folder 472-473)
      - Dust jacket, 1947
      - Books given out, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 474)
      - "Books and Ideas" column, 1947 (Box 15, Folder 475)
      - Fan mail, 1947-1975 (Box 15, Folder 476)
      - Reviews, 1947-1952 (Box 15, Folder 477)
    - The Complete Fly Fisherman (1970 and 1989 editions)
      - Correspondence
        - Borden, John, 1985-1986 (Box 15, Folder 478)
        - Gordon, Theodore, letters to Steven Wager (1913-1915), photocopies, 1986 (Box 15, Folder 479)
        - Heddon, Jack, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 480-482)